# Anant Hariharan

# Providence, RI, USA (607) 379-5103 — anant\_hariharan@brown.edu

#### **OBJECTIVE**

I am a structural seismologist with experience in the development, comparison, and interpretation of seismic observations of the Earth's interior. I seek to improve the fidelity of these images through developing improved methods for inversions and through improving the quality of the underlying datasets. My doctoral work explores improvements to seismic images made using long-period surface wave measurements via the elimination of sources of noise in these images.

#### **EDUCATION**

Brown University, Providence, RI Doctor of Philosophy, Geophysics

Expected August 2023

Brown University, Providence, RI Master of Science, Earth Sciences

May 2020

Cornell University, Ithaca, NY

May 2018

Summa Cum Laude, Bachelor of Arts

Double Majors in Physics and Geological Sciences, and Distinction in All Subjects

PUBLICATIONS Hariharan, A., C.A. Dalton. Minimizing Overtone Interference in Love Wave Phase Velocities: Application to USArray Data. In Review at GRL.

> Hariharan, A., C.A. Dalton, J.C. Babikoff, & G. Ekström. Controls on surface wave overtone interference. Geophysical Journal International, 228, 1665-1683, https://doi.org/10.1093/gji/ggab424, 2021.

> Nathan, E.M., A. Hariharan, D. Florez, & K.M. Fischer. Multi-Layer Seismic Anisotropy Beneath Greenland. Geochemistry, Geophysics, Geosystems, 22(5), e2020GC009512, https://doi.org/10.1029/2020GC009512, 2021.

> Hariharan, A., C.A. Dalton, Z. Ma, & G. Ekström. Evidence of overtone interference in fundamental-mode Rayleigh wave phase and amplitude measurements. Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth, 125(1), e2019JB018540, 2020.

> Mookherjee, M., J. Tsuchiya, A. Hariharan. Crystal structure, equation of state, and elasticity of hydrous aluminosilicate phase, topaz-OH (Al<sub>2</sub>SiO<sub>4</sub> (OH)<sub>2</sub>) at high pressures. Physics of the Earth and Planetary Interiors, 251, 24-35, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pepi.2015.11.006, 2016.

> Mookherjee, M., D. Mainprice, K. Maheshwari, O. Heinonen, D. Patel, A. Hariharan. Pressure induced elastic softening in framework aluminosilicate-albite (NaAlSi<sub>3</sub>O<sub>8</sub>). Scientific reports, 6(1), 1-10, https://doi.org/10.1038/srep34815, 2016.

# AWARDS

• Outstanding Student Presentation Award American Geophysical Union

2021

• NSF Graduate Research Fellowship National Science Foundation

2018 - 2023

• Hunter R. Rawlings III Cornell Presidential Research Scholar Cornell University

2016 - 2018

• Chester Buchanan Memorial Award Department of Earth and Atmospheric Sciences, Cornell University 2018

•	Tanner Dean's Scholar of the College of Arts and Sciences Cornell University, College of Arts and Sciences	2014 - 2018
•	Dean's List Cornell University	2014 - 2017
•	Michael William Mitchell Memorial Fund Award Department of Earth and Atmospheric Sciences, Cornell University	2017
•	Category Winner for Best Presentation Spring Research Forum, Cornell Undergraduate Research Board.	2017
•	SEG Scholarship Society of Exploration Geophysicists	2017

# RELEVANT EXPERIENCE

# Internship

Summer 2022-Present

# Sandia National Laboratories, Ground-Based Nuclear Detonation Detection Group, Albuquerque, NM

- Eliminated redundancy in global datasets of body-wave arrival times and inverted these datasets for global wavespeed models
- Identified systematic timing errors in global datasets of body-wave arrival times

# Research Experience

Jan 2016 - May 2018

# Cornell Earthquake Seismology Group, Ithaca, NY

 Processed body wave data recorded by seismometers deployed adjacent to the Main Ethiopian Rift to understand the impact of nearby rifting on crustal and upper mantle deformation.

# Summer Internship

Summer 2017

#### University of Maryland College Park, College Park, MD

 Developed a wavelet-based approach to quantify geographic variations in the spectra of heterogeneity present within global and regional tomographic models.

### Research Experience

May 2014 - May 2015

# Cornell Mineral Physics Group, Ithaca, NY

• Used crystallographic methods to interpret *ab initio* simulations and study the behavior of hydrous mineral phases occurring at high temperatures and pressures.

# SERVICE & LEADERSHIP

Reviewer for:

• Mechanical Systems and Signal Processing

2021-present

• Geophysical Journal International

2022-present

#### Organizer

#### Remote Online Sessions for Emerging Seismologists

2021 - present

• Planned lectures and organized course materials for an international, asynchronous course attended by 300+ students. Provided technical support and computing tutorials, as well as contributed to writing a grant for future sessions.

#### Student Representative

### American Geophysical Union Seismology Section

2020 - 2022

• Served on the executive committee for the Seismology Section. Helped curate and keep section website up-to-date and participated in section meetings and activities.

GeoClub Treasurer

2019 - 2020

 Managed finances for the Department of Earth, Environmental, and Planetary Sciences graduate students.

# Geophysics Seminar Organizer

2020

# Brown University, Providence, RI

• Organized a series of weekly geophysics lectures, including inviting scientists from other institutions.

# Writer and Editor, "The Research Paper" Science Literary Magazine

# Cornell University

2014 - 2018

• Wrote articles about Cornell University research for a broad audience. I was also selected to serve on the editorial board of this student-run publication for three years.

# Co-President, Earth and Atmospheric Sciences Student Association

# Cornell University

2015 - 2018

• Managed undergraduate student group finances and outreach activities, as well as organized multiple research symposia to showcase undergraduate research.

# **TEACHING & MENTORING**

Graduate Student Mentor,

Spring 2020-Present

#### Brown University, Providence, RI

• Helped advise an undergraduate student through a research project aimed at improving the quality of Rayleigh wave phase velocity measurements. Provided guidance with method development and coding. Project resulted in a poster at the American Geophysical Union Fall Meeting 2021.

Teaching Assistant

Fall 2021

# Brown University, Providence, RI

- Solid Earth Geophysics, EEPS 1610
- Responsible for grading all problem sets and answering student questions in thrice-weekly remote and in-person office hours, as well as asynchronously via Slack. I led two lab sessions, one of which I developed from scratch on surface-wave seismic tomography.

Course Assistant

Spring 2021

# Brown University, Providence, RI

- Natural Disasters, EEPS 0160M
- Created three video lectures on seismology and volcanology. Held weekly office hours.

#### **SKILLS**

Programming: Python, MATLAB, GMT, LATEX, Shell Scripting, SQL Developer,

**Field:** Familiar with broadband and nodal seismometer deployments and servicing. **Languages:** English (native), Spanish and Hindi (conversational).

Areas of Focus: Signal Processing, Inverse Theory, Data Mining, Structural Seismology

# RELEVANT

Earthquake Seismology, Advanced Seismology, Global Tectonics, COURSEWORK Solid Earth Geophysics, Rheology of the Crust and Mantle, Physical Volcanology, Structural Geology, Advanced Structural Geology, Earthquake Record Reading, Interior of the Earth, Geodynamics, Seismology, Active Tectonics, Advanced Seismology, Data Analysis in the Geosciences, Introduction to Biogeochemistry

> Quantitative: Continuum Physics of Solid Earth, Modeling in Natural Sciences, Computing using MATLAB, Multivariable Calculus for Engineers, Linear Algebra

for Engineers, Electromagnetism, Oscillations Wave and Quantum Physics, Thermodynamics, Basics of Quantum Mechanics, Applications of Quantum Mechanics, Intermediate Electricity and Magnetism

# SELECTED CONFERENCE PRESENTA-TIONS

**Hariharan, A.**, C. A. Dalton, Minimizing Love wave overtone interference in phase velocity measurements via a targeted selection of earthquake sources. AGU Fall Meeting 2021.

Russell, J. B., C. A. Dalton, & A. Hariharan, Array-based observations of Rayleigh-Wave attenuation in the Pacific. AGU Fall Meeting 2021.

J. Grossman, A. Hariharan, & C. A. Dalton, A new metric for improving the quality of Rayleigh wave phase-velocity Measurements, AGU Fall Meeting 2021.

Nathan, E.M., A. Hariharan, & K. M. Fischer. Greenland's mantle transition zone and crustal structure revealed by receiver functions, AGU Fall Meeting 2021.

**Hariharan**, A., C.A. Dalton, J.C. Babikoff, & G. Ekström. Controls on surface wave overtone interference, AGU Fall Meeting 2020.

**Hariharan, A.**, C.A. Dalton, Z. Ma, G. Ekström, & D. W. Forsyth. Overtone interference in fundamental-mode Rayleigh wave phase and amplitude, AGU Fall Meeting 2019.

Nathan, E.M., **A. Hariharan**, D. Florez, H.E. Krueger, I. Gama, J. Krogh, N. Zhao, & K.M. Fischer. Seismic anisotropy in the Greenland mantle from shear wave splitting, AGU Fall Meeting 2019.

**Hariharan**, A., V. Lekic, F. J. Simons, & P. Moulik (2019). An evolving multiscale repository of heterogeneity from the reconciliation of community Earth models, AGU Fall Meeting 2019.

# **FIELDWORK**

- Active Source Experimentation, Rio Grande, New Mexico 2017 Broadband seismometer servicing runs, and active-source profiling of the Socorro magma body
- Nodal Seismometer Retrieval in Oklahoma 2016 Retrieval of a massive rapid-response nodal deployment of seismometers to investigate aftershocks from the M5.8 Pawnee Quake.
- Broadband Seismometer Deployment in Oklahoma 2016
   Deployed broadband seismometers in Oklahoma for an array designed to monitor induced seismicity.
- Broadband Seismometer Servicing in Ithaca, New York 2016
  Serviced seismometers deployed in the Cornell Seismic Network to monitor instrument health and ensure continual recording of data, regardless of the number of snakes around the seismometers.
- Field Mapping in the Andes, Argentina 2015 Engaged in field mapping exercises in the Andes, including an independent mapping project. Worked in diverse geologic settings and recorded data for cross-sections, stereographic projections, and stratigraphic columns.